Guide to the Goldsboro Banyar and Banyar Family Papers 1727-1904 (bulk, 1740-1840) MS 39
New-York Historical Society
Goldsboro Banyar and Banyar Family papers
1727-1904 (bulk, 1740-1840)
New-York Historical Society
Banyar, Goldsbrow
Banyar (Family)
MS 39
91.4 Linear feet (31 boxes, 172 oversize folders)
This collection traces the estate and affairs of Goldsboro Banyar (1724-1815) and his heirs. As Deputy Secretary of pre-Revolutionary New York, Banyar played a significant role in colonial government, especially in the distribution of land grants. Papers include colonial government documents, business and personal correspondence, and a large number of 18th century land patents and indentures for property in New York and Vermont. The collection also includes papers relating to several generations of Banyar's heirs, including Campbell White (1787-1859), a successful New York merchant and politician, who married Goldsboro Banyar's granddaughter Harriet Banyar LeRoy.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of estate of Augustus Van Horne Stuyvesant, 1957.
Arrangement
The collection is organized chronologically in three series:
Series I, Goldsboro Banyar, spans the years from 1727-1775 and 1784-1823, documenting the political and business career of Goldsboro Banyar and his children.
Series II, Campbell P. White and Harriet (Banyar White), continues into the next generation with the papers of Campbell and Harriet (Banyar) White, the granddaughter of Goldsboro Banyar, covering the period from the 1820's to the 1850's.
Series III, Goldsborough Banyar (formerly John Campbell White), concludes with the papers of John Campbell White, the son of Campbell and Harriet, who changed his name to Goldsborough Banyar in order to inherit the Banyar estate. This series spans the period from the 1870's to 1904, and consists primarily of routine business correspondence concerning management of the various Banyar properties, accounts, tax and other receipts, and insurance policies.
Material within each series is arranged into subseries by subject matter and/or format, and within those categories, where possible, chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
This collection includes official and personal papers of Goldsboro (also spelled Goldsbrow, Goldsborow, Goldsborough) Banyar and his heirs, including prominent grandson-in-law Campbell White, a New York politician and businessman.
Goldsborough Banyar (1724-1815) emigrated from London to America in the 1730's. By 1746, he had become deputy to George Clarke, Secretary of the Colony of New York. He also served as Deputy Clerk of the Council and on the provincial Supreme Court. A shrewd businessman and adroit politician, Banyar had a hand in virtually every land transaction that took place in pre-Revolutionary New York, building valuable relationships and a considerable fortune.
In 1767, Banyar married Elizabeth Appy, widow of John Appy Esq., Secretary and Judge Advocate of His Majesty's Forces in America. Elizabeth was the step-daughter of Major Abraham Mortier, Paymaster-General of the British army in New York. (Mortier married Elizabeth's mother, the widow Martha Naden, after Elizabeth's father passed away. The Mortier's home, Richmond Hill, later became the headquarters of George Washington).
Goldsborough and Elizabeth had four or more children. It appears that only two survived to adulthood: a daughter, Martha, and son Goldsborough Banyar, Jr. The family lived in New York City until the onset of the Revolution, at which time they relocated to Rhinebeck, NY, in an attempt to avoid conflict. Although presumably a loyalist, Banyar managed to retain his many valuable grants of land. By 1790, the family had relocated again to Albany, where Banyar purchased a large home on Pearl Street as well as several other local properties. In 1800, the household included five slaves.
In 1801, Banyar's son, Goldsborough Banyar, Jr. married Maria Jay (1782-1856), daughter of John Jay (1845-1892), first Chief Justice of the United States. Banyar Jr. managed his father's extensive real estate holdings and served on local boards in Albany until 1806, when he died at the age of 31. Goldsboro Banyar, Senior, continued to live in Albany with his daughter-in-law, Banyar Jr.'s widow Maria. The elder Banyar died in 1815 at the age of 91.
By the time of Banyar's death, his only surviving child was his daughter Martha. Martha had married Jacob LeRoy, a prominent New York merchant, in 1792 The couple had three daughters -- Harriet, Mary, and Cornelia -- and a son, Goldsborough Banyar Leroy (1802-1866), who inherited his grandfather's extensive estate (as directed by Banyar's will, he changed his name from Goldsborough Banyar LeRoy to Goldsborough LeRoy Banyar).
Goldsborough LeRoy Banyar never married. His sister, Harriet Banyar LeRoy, married Campbell Patrick White. An Irish immigrant, Campbell Patrick White became a prominent New York lawyer and politician who served in Congress from 1829 to 1835. Campbell's brother, Robert White, served for many years as cashier of Manhattan Bank. The two brothers also managed the New York branch of the White family's distillery business, headquartered in Baltimore.
When Goldsborough LeRoy Banyar died in 1866, he left his estate to his nephew, John Campbell White (Campbell and Harriet White's son and Goldsboro Banyar's great-grandson). In accordance with his uncle Goldsborough LeRoy Banyar's will, John Campbell White also changed his name to Goldsborough Banyar in order to inherit the Banyar estate.
Scope and Contents
This collection traces the estate and affairs of Goldsboro Banyar and his heirs, spanning the period from the 1740's to 1904. The collection also includes papers relating to various members of the family of Campbell White, who married Goldsboro Banyar's granddaughter Harriet Banyar LeRoy. Materials include primary documents reflecting the governance of colonial New York; patents, deeds, and other documents relating to land transactions; business and personal correspondence; accounts; and legal and estate papers. Although primarily concerned with the affairs of prominent men, the collection also provides tantalizing glimpses of less-documented aspects of early American society, including slavery, interactions with Native Americans, relationships between landowners and laborers, and domestic affairs.
The collection is organized chronologically into three series. In addition to the general summary that follows, more detailed scope and contents notes are provided as introductory matter to each series. Series I spans the years from 1727-1775 and 1784-1823, documenting the political and business career of Goldsboro Banyar and his children, only one of whom (Martha, wife of Jacob LeRoy) survived at Banyar's death. This series consists primarily of documents relating to colonial administration, including office appointments, land transactions and the collection of quitrents, court fees, and rough minutes of Chancery Court proceedings, typically involving matters such as land disputes, estates, guardianship, and divorce. There is also post-colonial era correspondence relating to the settlement of British land claims and other business affairs. Correspondents include George Clarke (Secretary of New York), Edward Clarke, Sir William Johnson, William Knox, and family members Goldsboro Banyar, Jr., William Banyar, and Jacob LeRoy (Banyar's son-in-law). Notably, the only documents from the Revolutionary War period are several pieces of correspondence from the Commissioners for Conspiracies in 1778.
Series II continues into the generation of Goldsboro Banyar's granddaughter, Harriet (Banyar) White, covering the period from the 1820's to the 1850's. In 1816, Harriet married Irish immigrant Campbell White (1787-1859), a lawyer, politician, and business man, who apparently took over some or all responsibility for managing the Banyar estate. Papers in this series include family correspondence and receipts, as well as Campbell White's correspondence on political matters during and after his time in Congress (including a letter remarking on the assassination attempt on Andrew Jackson). Also included are business papers from the White family distillery, and correspondence and business papers of Campbell's brother, Robert White, who served as clerk of the Manhattan Bank for many years, resigning after the Panic of 1837 amid allegations of misfeasance. Notable subjects include currency and anti-rent legislation, the antebellum cotton trade, and the cholera outbreak of 1849.
Series III concludes with the papers of John Campbell White, the son of Campbell and Harriet and great-grandson of Goldsboro Banyar. John Campbell White changed his name to Goldsborough Banyar in order to inherit the Banyar estate. This series covers the period from the 1870's to 1904, and consists primarily of routine business correspondence concerning management of the various Banyar properties, accounts, tax and other receipts, and insurance policies.
Abstracts (summaries); Account books.; Accounts.; Affidavits.; Agreements; Bills of sale.; Bonds (legal records).; Certificates.; Conveyances.; Correspondence.; Daybooks; Diaries.; Estate records.; Indentures.; Land grants.; Land surveys.; Leases.; Letter books.; Lists (document genres); Maps.; Memorandums.; Minute books.; Minutes (administrative records); Mortgages.; Powers of attorney; Tax bills.; American loyalists; Boundaries (Estates); Cholera -- New York (State); Cotton trade -- United States.; Distilleries -- Maryland -- Baltimore.; Indentured servants -- New York (State); Indians Of North America -- Government relations.; Land grants -- New York (State).; Land settlement -- New York (State); Land subdivision -- New York (State); Land titles -- New York (State).; Land titles -- New York (State) -- Cherry Valley; Land titles -- New York (State) -- Mohawk River.; Land titles -- New York (State) -- Mohawk River Valley.; Land titles -- New York (State) -- Otsego County.; Land titles -- Registration and transfer -- New York (State); Land titles -- Vermont; Real property -- Cases; Real property surveys; Slavery -- New York (State).; Temperature measurements -- New York (State); New York (State) -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; New York (State) -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; New York (State) -- History -- 1775-1865.; New York (State) -- Politics and government -- To 1775.; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States -- History -- 1783-1865; Auditors.; Lawyers; Surveyors.; Anstey, John, -1819; Banyar, Goldsbrow; Banyar, William; Beekman, Henry, 1688-1776; Cholmondeley, Robert; Clarke, Edward, Major; Clarke, George, 1768-1835; Colden, Alexander, 1716-1774; Cooper, William, 1754-1809; Croghan, George, 1791-1849; Cruger, John Harris; De Lancey, Oliver, 1718-1785; Duane, James, 1733-1797; Ellice, Alexander; Etherington, Thomas, Major; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845; Johnson, William, 1715-1774; Kempe, John Tabor, -1791; Kennedy, Archibald, Captain; Le Roy, Jacob; Livingston, Robert, 1688-1775; McCormick, Daniel; Mortier, Martha; Porteous, John, -1809; Reade, Joseph, active 1765-1769; Remsen, Henry, 1736-1792; Scott, John Morin, 1730-1784; Stephens, Francis; Tryon, William, 1729-1788; Van Schaack, Peter, 1747-1832; Vaughan, John, Sir, 1747 or 1748-1795; Walpole, Horace, 1717-1797; Watts, John, 1749-1836; White, Campbell Patrick, 1787-1859; White, Robert, -1847; Woodbury, Levi, 1789-1851; Banyar (Family); Manhattan Bank (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I: Goldsboro Banyar
  - Subseries I.1: Colonial administration records
    Scope and Contents
    This subseries includes royal appointments of office to George Clarke, Senior (as Secretary of the province of New York) and to Goldsboro Banyar (as Clerk of the Court of Chancery), along with a deputation from George Clarke, Junior appointing Banyar Deputy Secretary of the province. The royal appointments are elaborate vellum documents with hand ornamentation and original seals still attached. Also included is a 1774 report to Governor William Tryon with information on the number of mines in the province, and its population (including a breakdown of whites and blacks), militia and government.
    Auditor's Office correspondence with auditors Thomas Smith, Horatio Walpole and Robert Cholmondeley relates to the collection of quit-rents, payment of salaries and other matters concerning the official accounts of New York.
    Also included are Banyar's drafts of decisions issued on motions and cases heard in Chancery Court. The Chancery Court was originally conceived as one that could rule on issues of fairness, and was not restricted to statutory law. Cases typically involved estate and business disputes, the resolution of land disputes, and divorce and other family matters, such as the appointment of a guardian for a minor. One case involved appointment of a committee to take care of a person "in a state of lunacy."
    There are also two bound volumes of minutes of Council proceedings relating to land transactions, spanning a two-year period from 1770 to 1772, and a list of wills filed in the Prerogative Office from 1769 to 1771.
    - Letters patent of King George II appointing George Clarke, Sr., Secretary of the Colony of New York, 1727/8 March 7 (Box OS large, Folder Banyar OS 1)
    - Letters patent of King George II appointing Goldsboro Banyar Register of Court of Chancery, 1742 August 6 (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS 2)
    - Letters patent of King George II appointing Goldsboro Banyar Register of Court of Chancery, 1753 May 5 (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS 3)
    - Letters patent of King George III appointing Goldsboro Banyar Register of Court of Chancery, 1770 June 11 (Box OS medium, Folder Banyar OS 4)
    - Letters patent, petitions, and deputations, 1745-1772 (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS 5)
      Includes letters from George Clarke and William Tryon to the Committee of the Privy Council regarding a controversy over the Prerogative Court
    - Deputations and reports, 1757, 1771, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes deputation from Rick Morris appointing Samuel Jones as Clerk of the Circuit; deputation from George Clarke appointing Goldsboro and William Banyar Deputy Secretary of State; and a report to Governor William Tryon on the present state and condition of New York (dated 1773)
    - Auditor's Office correspondence, 1746-1749 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Auditor's Office correspondence, 1750-1757 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Auditor's Office correspondence, 1757-1759 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Auditor's Office correspondence and accounts, 1760-1762 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Auditor's Office correspondence, 1763-1767 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Auditor's Office correspondence, 1768-1773 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Auditor's Office correspondence, 1774-1775, 1785, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Auditor's Office correspondence and related documents (OS), 1745-1768 (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS 6)
    - Court of Chancery, rough minutes, 1765-1770 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Court of Chancery, rough minutes, 1771-1773 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Court of Chancery, rough minutes, 1774-1776 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Minutes of Council in the Department of Land, 1770-1772 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - List of wills filed in the Prerogative Office of New York, 1769-1771 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Deposition of Goldsboro Banyar and John Bowles relating to assignment of deputy for Prerogative Court, 1770 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries I.2: Colonial administration accounts
    This subseries includes account books and loose accounts and receipts of court fees, monies relating to land transactions, and military expenses. Also included is an exchange note for 100 pounds sterling to recruit members of the Five Nations of Indians for a war against Canada, and a license and receipt for the purchase of land from Native Americans.
    - Account book, Goldsboro Banyar, 1746-1797 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Account of the profits of the Secretary's Office, 1751-1761 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Account of the profits of the Secretary's Office, 1764-1765, 1767-1772 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Chancery Court fees and rent rolls due to George Clarke, 1738-1774, undated (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS10)
    - John Chambers' account of fees due to George Clark, Clerk of the Supreme Court, 1745-1752 (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS8)
    - Accounts of attorneys' fees due to George Clarke, Clerk of the Supreme Court, 1747-1774 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Accounts of George Clarke, Clerk of the Supreme Court of the Province of New York, 1747-1773 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Accounts of George Clarke, Clerk of the Supreme Court of the Province of New York (Chancery Court fees), 1760-1774 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Receipts for fees due to Supreme Court Judges, 1763 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Accounts and receipt for fees to Judges and Attorneys, 1763-1773 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Accounts of fees due on first motions filed in Supreme Court of the Province of New York (OS), 1767-1774 (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS9)
    - Accounts of fees due on first motions filed in Supreme Court of the Province of New York (OS), 1763-1764 (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS8)
    - Accounts of Abraham Mortier, Paymaster General of the British Army, 1755-1766 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Accounts of Abraham Mortier, Paymaster General of the British Army (OS), 1755-1766 (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS7)
    - Accounts of Abraham Mortier, Paymaster General of the British Army, 1761-1767 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Account book, Abraham Mortier (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Papers relating to land of George Clarke, 1737-1745, 1798, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Fees for Land Patents, 1760-1774, 1792, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Exchange note issued in connection with measures to recruit the Five Nations of Indians to take part in an expedition against Canada, 1746 November 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - License to purchase lands from Native Americans, 1754, 1774 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Fragments of official papers, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Subseries I.3: Business and personal correspondence
    Scope and Contents Note
    This sub-series is arranged chronologically. Subseries I.3A, Colonial-era correspondence, consists primarily of Banyar's correspondence with George and Edward Clarke relating to administrative and financial matters. Matters discussed include Banyar's efforts to collect quit rents and salary owing to Clarke, his dispute with Archibald Kennedy, Receiver-General, about payment of Clarke's allowances and Clarke's right to the office of Register of the Prerogative Court, reports on the military and political situation in New York, frontier troubles, Indian problems and the war with the French. Other correspondents include Sir William Johnson and William Knox. A folder of general correspondence includes a 1763 letter discussing Thomas Stephens, the son of the Secretary of Georgia, and his inability to get "negroes" for the manufacture of potash.
    Subseries I.3B consists of post-Revolutionary correspondence, mostly dealing with business matters including the sale of lands, accounts, debts, suits, and stock purchases. Correspondence between Banyar and his son-in-law, Jacob LeRoy, includes personal observations on the outbreak of fever in Philadelphia and New York, and the inoculation of his children.
    - Subseries I.3A: Colonial-era correspondence
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1746-1749 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1750-1753 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1754-1756 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1757-1759 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1760-1762 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1763-1764 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1765-1766 June (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1766 July - 1767 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1768-1769 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1770 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1771 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1772-1773 June (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence with George Clarke, 1773 August - 1774 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence relating to accounts of George Clarke, 1792-1793, 1799 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence with Edward Clarke, 1750-1759 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence with Edward Clarke, 1760-1762 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence with Edward Clarke, 1763-1766 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence with Edward Clark, 1763 (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS 11)
      - Correspondence with Edward Clarke, 1767-1772 June (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence with Edward Clarke, 1772 July - 1773 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence with Edward Clarke, 1793-1801 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence with Sir William Johnson, 1765-1769 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence with Sir William Johnson, 1770-1772 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence with William Knox, 1773-1774 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - General correspondence of Goldsboro Banyar, 1749-1775 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Letters from Mr. Blenman, Christ College, 1770 (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS 11)
    - Subseries I.3B: Correspondence 1778-1823
      - Correspondence with and resolution of the Commissioners for Conspiracies, 1778 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - General correspondence, 1784-1794 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - General correspondence, 1795-1799 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - General correspondence, 1800-1801 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - General correspondence, 1802-1805 June (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - General correspondence, 1805 July - 1815, 1821 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence of Goldsbrow Banyar, Jr., 1799-1805 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence of William Banyar, 1783-1790 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence of William Banyar, 1791 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence of William Banyar, 1792-1805 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Letter from William Cooper to William Banyar, 1795 August 16 (Box OS small, Folder Banyar OS 11)
      - Correspondence to William Banyar from Garret and Jacob Benthuysen, 1791-1793 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence to William Banyar from Garret and Jacob Benthuysen, 1794-1795 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence of Jacob LeRoy, 1790-1794 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence of Jacob LeRoy, 1797 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence of Jacob LeRoy, 1798-1800 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence of Jacob Leroy, 1801-1802, 1805 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence of Jacob LeRoy, 1795-1796 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence of Francis Stephens, 1784-1787 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence of Francis Stephens, 1788-1794 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence of William H. Jephson, 1803-1823 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Subseries I.4: Daybooks and journals
    This subseries includes Goldsboro Banyar's private account books and notebooks of business transactions. There are also volumes with thermometer readings and daily weather notes.
    - Weather journals, 1762-1764, 1767-1768 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Daybooks, 1753, 1756-1758 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Daybooks, 1757, 1762-1768, 1783-1786 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Daybooks, 1786-1796 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Daybooks, 1787-1791, 1805-1809 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Daybook, 1809-1815 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Copybook, 1770-1780 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Copybook, 1803 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Subseries I.5: Patents, deeds and other land conveyances